<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-23T00:10:39+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Kamal’s Blog</title><subtitle>It is all about the knowledge</subtitle><author><name>Kamal Awasthi</name><email>kamalawasthi97@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Why do I think I should write</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/life-style/why-do-I-think-I-should-write/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why do I think I should write" /><published>2017-07-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-09-02T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/life-style/why-do-I-think-I-should-write</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/life-style/why-do-I-think-I-should-write/">&lt;p&gt;Well! let’s face this. We all have to start somewhere. Every famous name today was once an amateur learner.
In a video, Code Stars by code.org, Tech Giants have discussed that we all have to start from scratch. We do not need to wait for a miracle to happen. All we need is determination and a strong will to take the first step. The hardest part of the journey is the first step. Once you have taken that, you are already halfway there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Expect problems and eat them for breakfast”
-Alfred A. Montapert&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we start our journey, we face many new and exciting challenges. And as we are faced with a problem, we ought to seek its solution. We learn the most when we search the solutions for our problems. This process of “being stuck &amp;amp; seeking a solution”, is an indispensable part of learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s not that I’m so smart, it’s just that I stay with problems longer.”
-Albert Einstein&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I face many challenges when I sit down to try something new. I feel overjoyed as well as grateful when I see people who share their idea and work with the world. Blogs are like open source forums of art, ideas and freedom. They are the Stackoverflow of social writing with a liberty of saying anything you wish to. You can discuss whatever you want. You do not have to be bound to a particular question. There are questions and there are questions. All asked as well as answered by you. All original and unique, in your own way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to share my ideas, my thoughts and opinions with others. I am well aware of the fact that I am no well-versed scholar or a wise philosopher. I have not seen life much unlike many of you people out there. But, I believe all these are not required to be a blogger. Blogging is stating what is in your mind, straight and simple. It is an effort to help others to find and learn from what you have to say. It is a trick to tell people what they should do and how they should feel when they have a similar thought or challenge as you are having right now.
With all these notions, I want to start blogging. I would be sharing all my problems and all solutions I will find with my people, who read my content. I promise. &lt;em&gt;smile&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;wink&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamal Awasthi</name><email>kamalawasthi97@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Life-Style" /><category term="how-to" /><summary type="html">Well! let’s face this. We all have to start somewhere. Every famous name today was once an amateur learner. In a video, Code Stars by code.org, Tech Giants have discussed that we all have to start from scratch. We do not need to wait for a miracle to happen. All we need is determination and a strong will to take the first step. The hardest part of the journey is the first step. Once you have taken that, you are already halfway there.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">3 Step Guide to Time Managament</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/guides/A-Three-Step-Guide-to-Time-Management/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="3 Step Guide to Time Managament" /><published>2017-07-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-09-02T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/guides/A-Three-Step-Guide-to-Time-Management</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/guides/A-Three-Step-Guide-to-Time-Management/">&lt;p&gt;Time. When we say “Time” everyone goes like, “Oh! I waste a lot of time on unnecessary things, and end up regretting later”. Time management is one of the rarest and most important skills found in one. It requires discipline to follow an optimised routine for a prolific life style. So, Is it really tough to manage time? Is it really a deal of firm determination &amp;amp; great dedication to make a habit of good time management?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, It is but not if you do it with a proper action plan. I am here with 3 step process to manage your time better in three easy steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It takes 21 days to make a habit and 90 days to make a lifestyle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All you need is consistency. As discussed in a video on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VUk6LXRZMMk&quot;&gt;Time Management&lt;/a&gt; from the Wellcast team. We need to follow a three step process:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;RAC: Record, Analyse and Change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Record your day and try to make a list of mistakes you think you did which led you wasting you time. Do a budget. Pick 5 biggest mistakes of your day. Record them. These are the major reasons of your regrets when you think about how your day was before sleeping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analyze these mistakes and think what can you do about them. Try to change them. Write your mistakes into tabular form. Put three columns on the table. The first column will contain a short one line description of your mistake. The second one would be there for a one line analysis of the mistake, more like a comment or remark. And what can be done about it, how can you change this, will go into the last column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make a To-DO List and prioritize it. Do not go overboard with enthusiasm. Try to be limited to 5 tasks per day. And try to finish them by the end of the day. It gives us confidence and happiness when we set up goals and complete them in a given time-limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Declutter and set timelines for each task. Set the start and stop point. Try to adhere to your To-Do List and time line you prepared. Set alarms and reminders. Do not be a victim of Procrastination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discipline is the key if it’s a good life style you wish to accomplish.
Best of luck.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamal Awasthi</name><email>kamalawasthi97@gmail.com</email></author><category term="guides" /><category term="guides" /><summary type="html">Time. When we say “Time” everyone goes like, “Oh! I waste a lot of time on unnecessary things, and end up regretting later”. Time management is one of the rarest and most important skills found in one. It requires discipline to follow an optimised routine for a prolific life style. So, Is it really tough to manage time? Is it really a deal of firm determination &amp;amp; great dedication to make a habit of good time management?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What do I know about Emotional INtelligence but you dont</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/life%20style/What-do-I-Know-About-Emotional-Intelligence-But-You-Dont/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What do I know about Emotional INtelligence but you dont" /><published>2017-07-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-09-02T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/life%20style/What-do-I-Know-About-Emotional-Intelligence-But-You%20Dont</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/life%20style/What-do-I-Know-About-Emotional-Intelligence-But-You-Dont/">&lt;p&gt;Human Mind is the most complex and mysterious machinery found in the World. It handles and is capable of handling much more than we can imagine. We think our mind is used only in thinking, logical reasoning, taking decisions, recognising and remembering and in all those things we do consciously. But this little but the most complex thing in the world, does much more than this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, we have two minds. In simpler terms, we have two nature of same mind. First one is “&lt;strong&gt;Logical Mind&lt;/strong&gt;” which we all are familiar with and the other one is “&lt;strong&gt;Emotional Mind&lt;/strong&gt;”. While Logical Mind is responsible for more rational and toughtful decisions, Emotional Mind governs sudden reflexes in response of something it captures. Emotional Mind is more volatile and it easily reflects whatever it feels into our actions. It tricks us into showing sudden irrational behaviour or some actions which were not really neccessary at the the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But surprisingly, during the course of evolution of today’s modern age human beings from its early-age marine life, the Emotional Brian developed much before than the logical brain started developing. &lt;strong&gt;Daniel Goleman&lt;/strong&gt; talks about this evolution of logical brain from the emotional one into detail in his book, “&lt;strong&gt;Emotional Intelligence. Why it can Matter more than IQ&lt;/strong&gt;”. Infact this whole post is inspired from his book which talks about the relevance of emotional intelligence in our lives and how we should take care of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Life is comedy for those who think and a tragedy who for those who feel” &lt;br /&gt;
-Horace Walpole&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emotional Brain is responsible for more-of reflex types of reactions. It has its roots in the early stage, i.e. much simpler forms of minds, which developed into species which showed on earth much before Human Beings. It forces us to react totally on the basis of how we feel without letting us to evalutate the situations correctly. Emotional brain works on a simple technique. It would simply ask,”What is this, I don’t like it. oh! I am not feeling good. I am hurt. Am I hurt?” and somehow it will jump to a conclusion that yes this is somthing which should be avoided, and would immediately give us instruction to act without giving it much tought or weighing the situation correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, this simply &lt;strong&gt;DOES NOT&lt;/strong&gt; mean that we should ignore our emotional intelligence(or brain) completely as it can be faulty sometime. Take an example of a person who has a very good IQ score. He can be very smart at maths or could solve very difficult puzzles in seconds but this does not imply that one would be as successful in one’s life as in academic field. Life involves many other factors and some of them have emotional aspect too. Infact, IQ contributes to 20% to the factors that determine life success, hence this means 80% involvement is of other forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the questions arises here is: Can Emotion be Intelligence? and the answer is &lt;strong&gt;YES&lt;/strong&gt;. A person with average IQ score can be more sucessful than a person really smart at logical thinking. All that is required is a Little &lt;strong&gt;Self-Awareness&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“KNOW THYSELF”&lt;br /&gt;-Socrates&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is a boon for someone who knows Self-Awareness and a total tragedy for one who doesn’t. Frued has desribed it as “&lt;strong&gt;evenly hovering attention&lt;/strong&gt;”. Daniel Goleman has talked about it in his book as, &lt;strong&gt;an interested yet unreactive witness&lt;/strong&gt;. Some psycho-analysts call it the “&lt;strong&gt;observing ego&lt;/strong&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Daniel Goleman describes, Self-awareness is not an attention that gets carried away by emotions or overreaction. Rather, it is neutral mode that maintains self-reflectiveness amidst turbulent emotions. It is just keeping a check on your emotions so that thay do not get ahead of us and do not overshadow our logical mind. We should always listen to our emotional mind but with a neutral sense without getting a biased approach. Sometime it can give us the faulty perception, but it also gives us the required empathy and neccessary emotions required to interect with others, undersatnd someone or some situation, and make others feel the warmth we have for them in our heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is just that we should always check our emotions and correctly evaluate whatever we are feeling at the the moment. Sometime, we can feel the anger boiling in our mind, we can handle that situation with a little self-awareness. We can calm down our self, just by giving instruction to our emotional mind, “this is the anger I am feeling may be I should think about this after some time.” or we can simply say, “This is anger and this is not good let it pass first then I will think”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just Remember, “Down as well as Ups spice life, but need to be in balance.” Similarly, We need logical as well as Emotional brain, but in perfect balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The above blog is completely inspired from Daniel Goleman’s book, “Emotional Intelligence. Why it can matter more than IQ”. All these techniques and examples are based on the book. You should read the book for detailed coverage of each aspect discussed in the blog above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed reading, please do share the post and tell me about your thoughts in comments below.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamal Awasthi</name><email>kamalawasthi97@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Life Style" /><category term="guides" /><category term="how-to" /><category term="jekyll" /><category term="github" /><summary type="html">Human Mind is the most complex and mysterious machinery found in the World. It handles and is capable of handling much more than we can imagine. We think our mind is used only in thinking, logical reasoning, taking decisions, recognising and remembering and in all those things we do consciously. But this little but the most complex thing in the world, does much more than this.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why do I think I should write</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/now/What-Am-I-Doing-Now/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why do I think I should write" /><published>2017-07-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-09-02T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/now/What%20Am%20I%20Doing%20Now</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/now/What-Am-I-Doing-Now/">&lt;p&gt;Well! let’s face this. We all have to start somewhere. Every famous name today was once an amateur learner.
In a video, Code Stars by code.org, Tech Giants have discussed that we all have to start from scratch. We do not need to wait for a miracle to happen. All we need is determination and a strong will to take the first step. The hardest part of the journey is the first step. Once you have taken that, you are already halfway there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Expect problems and eat them for breakfast”
-Alfred A. Montapert&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we start our journey, we face many new and exciting challenges. And as we are faced with a problem, we ought to seek its solution. We learn the most when we search the solutions for our problems. This process of “being stuck &amp;amp; seeking a solution”, is an indispensable part of learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s not that I’m so smart, it’s just that I stay with problems longer.”
-Albert Einstein&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I face many challenges when I sit down to try something new. I feel overjoyed as well as grateful when I see people who share their idea and work with the world. Blogs are like open source forums of art, ideas and freedom. They are the Stackoverflow of social writing with a liberty of saying anything you wish to. You can discuss whatever you want. You do not have to be bound to a particular question. There are questions and there are questions. All asked as well as answered by you. All original and unique, in your own way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to share my ideas, my thoughts and opinions with others. I am well aware of the fact that I am no well-versed scholar or a wise philosopher. I have not seen life much unlike many of you people out there. But, I believe all these are not required to be a blogger. Blogging is stating what is in your mind, straight and simple. It is an effort to help others to find and learn from what you have to say. It is a trick to tell people what they should do and how they should feel when they have a similar thought or challenge as you are having right now.
With all these notions, I want to start blogging. I would be sharing all my problems and all solutions I will find with my people, who read my content. I promise. &lt;em&gt;smile&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;wink&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamal Awasthi</name><email>kamalawasthi97@gmail.com</email></author><category term="now" /><category term="how-to" /><summary type="html">Well! let’s face this. We all have to start somewhere. Every famous name today was once an amateur learner. In a video, Code Stars by code.org, Tech Giants have discussed that we all have to start from scratch. We do not need to wait for a miracle to happen. All we need is determination and a strong will to take the first step. The hardest part of the journey is the first step. Once you have taken that, you are already halfway there.</summary></entry></feed>